Guide to the Matt Phillips collection of prints and drawings, 1953-2008 M1047
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Matt Phillips collection of prints and drawings
1953-2009
M1047
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
10.0 Linear feet (16 flat boxes, 3 boxes, 1 framed item)
Collection of prints, drawings, photographs and papers of Matt Phillips.
Phillips, Matt, 1927-
Access
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession numbers: 1999-087, 1999-319, 2000-010, 2000-070, 2000-071, 2000-103, 2000-110, 2000-174, 2000-175, 2000-294, 2000-295, 2000-313, 2001-031, 2001-121, 2001-301, 2001-302, 2001-344, 2001-345, 2002-071, 2002-107, 2002-283, 2002-284, 2003-005, 2003-122, 2003-143, 2003-327, 2003-328, 2004-011, 2004-012, 2004-289, 2004-290, 2004-347, 2005-330, 2005-347, 2006-040, 2006-252, 2006-259, 2006-260, 2006-338, 2007-090, 2007-091, 2007-160, 2007-266, 2008-042, 2008-043, 2008-146, 2008-147, 2008-332, 2008-333, 2008-338, 2009-034, 2009-035, 2009-172, 2009-173
Materials were part purchase and part gift from Matt Phillips between 1999 and 2009.
Biography
Matt Phillips was born in New York City in 1927. He initially pursued a career as a poet and, in 1952, earned an M.A. in literature from the University of Chicago. At the same time, he was studying art at the Barnes Foundation in Merion, Pennsylvania. Not content with the collections of modern art in the U.S., Phillips traveled throughout Europe and studied painting in the museums and studios there. He taught briefly in Paris but returned to the U.S. in 1964 to teach at Bard College in New York. Having retired from Bard in 1987, he now devotes his time to exhibitions, travel and guest lectures.
Scope and Contents note
Materials are mostly described at the item level.
DeMerritt, John; diebenkorn, Richard, 1922-1993; Editions Koch.; Hays, Susannah; Herrick, Robert, 1591-1674; Holub, Leo, 1916-; Milton, Avery; Peters, Rebecca; Phillips, Matt, 1927-; American art--20th century.; Art, Modern; Art, Modern--20th century--California.; Drawings.; Prints.
- Self-portrait, 1993. "Winds of Montana": set of 6 artist's proofs, chine colle drypoints, black and white, 1998. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Markets: a suite of 8 drypoints, 1993. Subjects include Egypt, Morocco, Guatemala, Mexico. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Napa suite": six handcolored drypoints, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Garden interlude": six handcolored drypoints, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 3 photographs of Phillips and Robert Kelly by Susannah Hays, nd; 4 lithographs [Paris], 1963; 1 watercolor, 1953. (Box 2)
- "Women in the Studio": portfolio of 6 original black and white lithographs and 2 handcolored lithographs, 1976 (artist's proof set). (Box 3)
- 3 drawings, 1980. "Walking the Dog": lithograph printed at Atelier Clot on Rives BFK, ed. 14 of 50, 1963. Artist's proof of yellow nude with red hair, 1995. "Gil Williams": artist's proof, 1979. Sketchbook made at Machu Pichu, April, 1999. 2 black and white photographs of Phillips by Leo Holub, nd. Color photocopy of photograph of Phillips at Machu Pichu, April, 1999. Joyce Carol Oates' "The Stone Orchard", a broadside designed by Grant Dahlstrom and illustrated by Phillips, 1980; and an original lithographic poster for a Phillips exposition, Librairie Anglaise, signed, 1964. It also includes "Flower studies," 1 artist book, 1991; and 5 prints, crayon studies framed in one unit, ca 1953-1955 (Box 4)
- "Guatemalan Market Suite": boxed set of eight colored monotypes, 1977. Untitled set of 18 prints, boxed, 1980. (Box 5)
- "Through the rain, Greece": etching, 7/12, 1970; "Promenades": etching, 1964; "Family outing": lithograph, 1964; "Two shoppers": lithograph, 1963; two untitled artist's proofs, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- "Dreamer," e/a, and "Dreamer and family," e/a, two-sided lithograph, 1962. "First lithographs," 1962 or 1963, e/a, four on one sheet. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- "Etudes," 8 drypoints on copper plates, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Four lithograph proofs of Paris exhibit poster (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Drawing studies (5 sheets), 1970, 1984, 1989, nd (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Woman at table (3 pencil drawings), 1980-1981; "A celebration": collage and paint on black wash, 2001; Monotype (green, blue & brown), 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- " California landscape": monotype, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Two female figures at art show: lithograph, (3 prints colored differently), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- " Paris vignettes," each #2, 1963; "First lithographs," each (4 on one sheet), 1962 or 1963; "Studio scenes," lithograph 10/11, 1963; self-portrait, collage, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- "Promenades, Paris": lithograph, e/a, 1963; "Paris fantasy": lithograph, e/a, 1964; "Large Promenades, Paris": lithograph, 5/30, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- 27 color photographs of a Moroccan market, 1982. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Biographical information about Matt Phillips, 4 articles by Phillips, "Gritchenko," 1964, "Maurice Prendergast," 1967, "Essay on Milton Avery," 1971, and "The Monotype," 1972; exhibit catalogs, 1972-1988; exhibit announcements, 1957-2000, 12 original studies for a wine label, 1990, 7 prints, 1963-1970, 2 studies for the 1991 Limestone Press book, 4 photographs, 1966-1985, prototype for the Limestone Press edition of an unfinished book that contains 13 handprinted flower monotypes based on Robert Herrick's poem "The Argument of His Book," 1991; and 1 pencil and crayon study, untitled, 1994. (Box 7)
- 1. Napa: monotype print book with 64 monotype prints, 1992. Handsewn by Susannah Hays. 2. A unique book of 10 monotype prints, 1991. Designed by Susannah Hays. 3. 9 drypoints, 1963 and 1970; and 1 lithograph, 1963 4. Working drawings (8 total, 4 on each side of a sheet of sketch paper), 2003; a woodcut print of 4 figures and a tree (artist's proof #1), a color photographic print, "Still life with sketchbook," 2003; and "Study for illustration of Keats' Ode on a Grecian Urn" (artist's proof #1), 2002. 5. Scroll of monotypes in blue box, 1991. (Box 8)
- 1. "Still-lifes": portfolio. 4 black & white drypoints and 1 handcolored drypoint from an edition of 12. Copy # 2, 2002 & 2003. 2. " Montana": portfolio. 6 handcolored drypoints, 2003. Folder 3. "Still lifes II," portfolio of 6 b/w lithographs, 1 water colour lithograph. Artist proofs, 2003. "Big Sky": 6 drypoints in a portfolio, 2003. (Box 9)
- "Lovers in a park": collage/monotype, 1 of series, 2003. Sketches for "Clouds" and "Big Sky": portfolio, 2003. (Box 10, Folder 1)
- "Big Sky": 6 drypoints from a drypoint series of 4 in blue portfolio case, Sept. 2003. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- "Garden interludes series of Kim Morrison": 5 monotype collages, 2003. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- "Israel": six hand-colored dry points in portfolio case, 1993. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- "Ode on a Grecian Urn": 3 artist's proof prints on Japanese paper printed by Kay Bradner for Matt Phillips, 2004, and one hand-colored print, 2004. "Painter Poet": collage/monotype, signed, 2004. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- " Montana": watercolor, signed, 2001. "The Entertainer": monotype, signed, 2004. "Painter at rest": collage/monotype, signed, 2004. "Painter Poet": collage/monotype, signed, 2004. Two monoprints, # II and V, signed, 2000. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- "For Vanessa": watercolor, signed, 2000. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- "Pas de Deux": 20 digital photographs and 2 handprinted monotypes in portfolio, 2006. (Box 12)
- "Homage to Prendergast": monotype, 1967. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Two colored collages, 2005 and 2006. (Box 13, Folder 2)
- "Montana V": monoprint, 2000. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Improvisational studies: "The lady blue," and "untitled." (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Collage/drawing, "Figure under a tree," 2007. Three monotypes given in memory of Phillips' first wife, Lois Marcia Shapiro Phillips: "Figure under a tree," 1961; "Under the umbrella," 1962; and "Market triptych," 1966. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- "Six Nudes," two boxed sets of dry point prints, six black and white, and six colored, 2006. (Box 14)
- "The Song of Solomon," twelve drypoints printed by Rebecca Peters and hand-colored by the artist, Matt Phillips. Text printed by Editions Koch, Berkeley, 2007. Text and drypoints in a clamshell box decorated with a relief print by Matt Phillips. (Box 15)
- 2 loose monotypes: monotype collage, nd, and monotype print untitled, 2007; 1 folder (5 monotype prints: The bather, 1966; New York 5th Avenue: study for screen, 1977; Apple & bottle, 1961; self-portrait collage, 2007; self-portrait collage, 2008). Folder 2. 3 pencil sketches / drawings. Folder 3. 2 matted watercolor prints. Folder 4. 2 watercolor prints signed by Phillips, untitled beach scenes with nude figures, 1972. (Box 16)
- 1) "Little blue," boxed set of 5 hand colored drypoints, 2007-2008, and 1 color photograph of model used for drypoint images; all signed by artist; 1 of 5 produced; 2) "Still life," boxed set of 4 hand colored drypoints, 2008, and 1 color photograph; all signed by artist; 1 of 5 produced; 3) Folder with 3 monotypes (nude, 1960, first monotype print in Phillip's collection; market scene, 1970, self-portrait monotype collage, 2007). (Box 17)
- "All that jazz," twelve drypoints printed by Rebecca Peters and hand-colored by Matt Phillips. Text printed by Editions Koch, Berkeley, 2008. Text and prints in box created by John DeMerritt. (Box 18)
- Three color crayon sketches, 1994; one crayon and watercolor painting, 1994. 1. Small oil painting of Bucks County farm scene, mounted on masonite, [early 1950s]; 2. Photograph of Richard Diebenkorn with Phillips in Diebenkorn's studio, 1953; 3. Four early monotypes: Paris market, Resting figure, Don Quixote, and The little hunters, all 1962; 4. Vietnam street scene, monotype over dry point, 1905-1907; 5. Explosion in a garden, collage/monotype, 2005; 6. Nude on a patterned rug, collage/monotype, 2008 (2 versions); 7. Couple, collage/monotype, 2008; 8. Six studies of flowers printed by hand (spoon) on Japan paper, 2001; 9. Figure with irises, collage/monotype, 2009; 10. Five oil sketches over digital photographs, circa 2000; 11. Two monotypes: Marrakesh market entrance and A garden, [1960s]; 12. Reclining figure under trees, small monotype, nd. (Box 19)
- 1 ink and watercolor of hayfield near Stanford University, signed by Phillips, [1953]. Given in memory of Lois Marcia Shapiro Phillips, 2008. [framed] (Frame 1)